In this video, we'll cover one, actions Amazon takes to address restricted
products policy violations, two, addressing restricted products policy
violations, and three, best practices to remain compliant.
Note that this module
was developed specifically for sellers operating in the US and provides an
overview of US policies.
Policies in other countries would vary.
Refer to the
restricted products help pages in your local seller central account.
Restricted
products policies are put in place to protect Amazon's customers from products
that are illegal, illegally marketed, unsafe, offensive, or prohibited by Amazon's
policies.
These policies also give customers confidence that all products
available for purchase in the Amazon store are compliant with local laws and
regulations.
Further, within the US there could be state-specific guidelines.
For
example, some products are subject to additional regulation in the state of
California.
Make sure to check that your listings comply with all policies for
each country where you sell.
Let's first review actions Amazon takes against
restricted product policy violations.
Amazon constantly works with regulators,
third-party experts, and selling partners to improve and innovate on behalf of
customers and ensure that any listings that violate applicable laws or
regulations or Amazon's restricted product policies are dealt with seriously.
If any
listing is in violation with Amazon's policies we will take corrective action
as appropriate which may include immediately removing the listing from
your catalog, suspending or terminating your selling privileges, destroying
inventory in our fulfillment centers without reimbursement, returning
inventory, terminating the business relationship and permanent withholding
of payments.
Further, the sale of any illegal or unsafe products could result
in legal action.
Please ensure that all of your listings are compliant with these
policies and local laws and regulations.
Please also note that Amazon updates our
restricted products policies and help pages to reflect continuously changing
laws and regulations.
We attempt to notify our selling partners in advance of
these changes via email and when applicable via the Seller Central News
widget, newsletter, and forums.
When possible, we proactively notify selling
partners with clear expectations of the time period to sell through their
inventory before removing the detail pages.
In some cases, Amazon needs to take
immediate action and our help pages are updated with revised policies.
Hence, it
is always a good practice to frequently review the policy pages relevant to
your products to ensure that you are in compliance.
If you discover listings that
are in violation with our policies or applicable laws, you can contact us.
Please
visit the category, product, and listing restrictions help page to find more
information and relevant links on how you can report a violation.
Based on the
type of violation, you may need to provide information to facilitate an
investigation.
This may include the store or business name of the seller you are
reporting, the ASIN, relevant marketplaces where the violation is taking place, an
explanation detailing the violation and any other supporting documentation.
You
will also be required to provide your email and contact number.
Next, let's
review how to respond to a restricted products policy violation notice.
If you
receive a notification that your ASIN or product was removed due to a
restricted products violation, please read the full performance notification and
check the policy help pages to understand why your ASIN or product might have been
removed.
Depending on the nature of the notice, you can take several actions to
review, resolve, and reduce your future risk of account deactivation.
The
performance notifications page can be found under the performance tab in the
seller central main menu.
This page shows many of the account deactivation and
listing level violation enforcements and messaging.
Selling partners could also
receive notifications via other channels such as email.
If you believe that your
product or ASIN was removed in error, you may appeal using the account health
dashboard.
To do this, hover over the performance tab in the seller central main
menu, then select account health.
Removed ASINs can be reviewed and appealed under
product policy compliance.
Before you contact seller support, please ensure
that you have followed all the instructions in your restricted products
performance notification and have provided all of the documentation and/or
evidence requested.
Make sure to respond to individual ASIN level
violations in a timely manner to help prevent account deactivation.
To access
more details on this topic, visit the additional information and resources for
sellers about our restricted products policy help page.
Here are some helpful
tips for selling partners to ensure that they remain compliant with local laws
and Amazon policies.
Keep product pages about the product and ensure that the
detail pages are accurate.
Carefully review our restricted products policy
help pages and your product catalog on a regular basis to ensure that your
products are compliant.
Don't forget about products included in inventory
feeds or those that are uploaded using an automated system.
Check the news widget
and seller forums periodically for any notified changes.
Also make sure to check
your messages under performance notifications for any specific policy
related changes.
A product may still not be permitted even if it is not
expressly listed on our restricted products policy help page.
Assign someone
to carefully review each product you are listing to ensure it is compliant.
When
buying inventory from another source apart from the manufacturer, make sure to
understand the sourcing and origin of the product and take care to understand the
legal framework in which the product or products may be sold.
If selling
supplements or eligible drugs confirm that the ingredients are compliant not
just with our policies but with FDA regulations and guidelines.
The FDA
orange book on prescription and OTC drugs and the FDA green book on animal
drugs are helpful sources.
Make sure to also check the list of recalls, market
withdrawals and safety alerts on the FDA website.
Sellers participating in the
fulfillment by Amazon or FBA program should comply with additional FBA specific
product restrictions in addition to Amazon's restricted products policies.
These include hazardous materials and substances regulated by the Narcotics
Act.
For instance the sale of vehicle tires and alcoholic beverages are
prohibited for sale by FBA.